# Ana Luísa Pinho

**BrainsCAN Postdoctoral Fellow** 

Western Interdisciplinary Research Building, room 4130 Western University, Dock 76 1151 Richmond St N London, Ontario N6A 3K7, Canada

https://alpinho.github.io

@ agrilopi@uwo.ca

G Google Scholar: ana.luisa.pinho

**ORCID**: 0000-0001-8718-0902

### About Me -

I am a Neuroscientist with a background in Engineering Physics. My research focuses on the application of functional Magnetic Resonance Imaging (fMRI), computational and statistical techniques—including machine learning— to map neurocognitive mechanisms in the human brain.

# Expertise

Plan&Organize Multistep Projects

Analysis of High-Dimensional Data

Scientific Writing

# Languages

Portuguese

**English** 

French



### Social Network -



@alpinho

@ALuisaPinho@fediscience.org

@ALuisaPinho

linkedin.com/in/analuisapinho

# Memberships -



Member of the Portuguese Society for Neuroscience

### **Professional Experience**

2021 - Present Tier I BrainsCAN Postdoctoral Fellow

Western University, CA

- Functional mapping of the cortico-striatal-cerebellar circuitry involved in the cognitive ability of forming temporal predictions during rhythmic and non-rhythmic sequences of events.
- Development of individualized encoding models (that better account for inter-subject variability) to improve functional specificity in neuroimaging of the cognitive mapping of elementary components associated with human behaviour.

2015 – 2020 Postdoctoral Researcher

Parietal Team - Inria Saclay, FR

- Development of the Individual Brain Charting (IBC) dataset, an open-access, multi-task fMRI-data initiative.
- Development of an individual-functional-atlasing approach to link functional segregation of specialized brain regions to elementary mental functions, by leveraging the IBC dataset.

#### **Education**

Postgraduate

2009 - 2015 PhD

Karolinska Institutet, SE and University of Coimbra, PT

**Biomedical Sciences** 

Thesis: Inside of the Creative Mind: Unravelling the Neurocognitive Mechanisms of Musical Creativity

Undergraduate

1999 – 2008 MSc + Licentiate Degrees

Instituto Superior Técnico – ULisboa, PT

**Engineering Physics** 

Thesis: Probabilistic non-linear earthquake location in a 3–D velocity model

# Fellowships, Grants & Awards

2021 - Present BrainsCAN Postdoc. Fellowship Canada First Research Excellence Fund, CA

Amount (5y): 389K CAD

2013 – 2014 **Research Fellowship** Sven and Dagmar Saléns Foundation, SE

Amount:  $\sim$ **144K SEK** 

2013 Prize of The Best Poster Communication Rectory of NOVA ULisboa, PT

Symposium "Music, Poetry & The Brain - Celebrating Wagner's Bicentennial"

2009 – 2013 **PhD Studentship** Foundation for Science and Technology, PT

**SFRH/BD/33895/2009** Amount: ~**80K** €

2006 – 2007 Scientific Initiation Grant Fou

Seismology

Amount: ~**3.600** €

Foundation for Science and Technology, PT

#### **Ad Hoc Reviewer**

Journals

Cerebral Cortex, NeuroImage, Scientific Data, Scientific Reports, Brain Structure and Function, Brain Imaging and Behavior, Frontiers in Psychology and PeerJ Computer Science

# Ana Luísa Pinho

BrainsCAN Postdoctoral Fellow

# Computer Skills —

#### Programming

Python (venv, pytest, Joblib), Bash, C, SQL, Lisp, Assembly (Harvard Arquitecture)

#### Scientific Computing

IPython, NumPy, SciPy, pingouin, MATLAB, GNU Octave, Jupyter Notebook, R, Wolfram Mathematica

#### Machine-Learning Frameworks

scikit-learn, PyTorch, Google AI&ML Transformers

#### ☐ Data Maniputation Visualization ☐

pandas, Matplotlib, Seaborn

#### A Typesetting

LETEX(Document Classes: article, beamer, book and letter)

#### Software for Neuroimaging

Nilearn, NiBabel, SPM, FSL, FreeSurfer, Papaya, Connectome Workbench, MRIcron, MRIcroGL, BrainVoyager

### Software for Psychophysics

Expyriment, pliers, Psychtoolbox, E-Prime&E-Basic, PsychoPy, Presentation

### Software Engineering

Git protocol (Platforms: GitHub and GitLab), Conda

### Web/Databases

HTML&CSS, Django

#### # Miscellaneous

GNU Emacs, gnuplot, Visual Studio Code, Office productivity softwares, GIMP, Inkscape, darktable, Unison File Synchronizer, VeraCrypt, FFmpeg, Kdenlive, Statistica

#### **Selected Publications**

2024 Individual Brain Charting third release, probing brain activity during Movie Watching and Retinotopic Mapping.

> Ana Luísa Pinho et al. Sci Data. 11(1):590

2024 Should one go for individual or group-level brain parcellations?

A deep-phenotyping benchmark.

Bertrand Thirion, Himanshu Aggarwal, Ana Fernanda

Ponce, Ana Luísa Pinho, and Alexis Thual Brain Struct Funct. 229(1):161-181

2021 From deep brain phenotyping to functional atlasing.

Bertrand Thirion, Alexis Thual, and Ana Luísa Pinho

Curr Opin Behav Sci. 40:201-202

2021 Subject-specific segregation of functional territories based on

> deep phenotyping Ana Luísa Pinho et al.

Hum Brain Mapp. 42(4):841-870

Individual Brain Charting dataset extension, second release of 2020

high-resolution fMRI data for cognitive mapping.

Ana Luísa Pinho et al. Sci Data. 7(1):353

2018 Individual Brain Charting, a high-resolution fMRI dataset for cog-

> nitive mapping Ana Luísa Pinho et al. Sci Data. 5:180105

#### Selected Dataset Publications

2021 **Individual Brain Charting (IBC)** 

Ana Luísa Pinho et al. EBRAINS, v3.0

2020 Individual Brain Charting dataset extension, second release of

high-resolution fMRI data for cognitive mapping

Ana Luísa Pinho et al.

NeuroVault, id collection=6618

### **Selected Software Contributions**

2021 - Present Contributer to WiNRepo: "Women in Neuroscience Repository" 2017 – Present Contributer to **Nilearn**: Stats&ML for NeuroImaging in Python 2015 – Present Contributer to Public Analysis Code for the IBC Project 2015 – 2020 Contributer to **Public Protocols for the IBC Project** 

#### **Selected Talks**

Deep behavioral phenotyping in functional MRI for cognitive 2023

mapping of the human brain

Seminar at the MNI Feindel Brain and Mind Lecture Series, BIC and

MNI, McGill University, Montreal, Canada

2020 Segregation of functional territories in individual brains

Oral presentation in Session Modeling and Analysis: Variability in

Brain Activation, OHBM Annual (Virtual) Meeting

2020 Individual Brain Charting dataset extension: second and third

Open Science Room, OHBM Annual (Virtual) Meeting

2019 Individual Brain Charting, a high-resolution fMRI dataset for

cognitive mapping of the human brain The 5<sup>th</sup> CiNet Conference, Osaka, Japan

## **Advocacy**

Gender Equity Board member of the Women in Neuroscience Repository (WiNRepo)

October 28, 2024

Ana Luísa Pinho